Curtis Cook Zuni Pueblo storytelling collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Curtis Cook Zuni Pueblo storytelling collection 1964-2005
AFC 2004/010
Cook, Curtis D.
1,272 items
5 sound tape reels: analog; 7 in.
1 sound cassette: analog.
196 slides: color; 35 mm
2 photographic prints: black and white; various sizes.
18 photographic prints: color.
53 folders.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of field recordings, photographs, and notes by linguist Curtis Cook, who learned the Zuni language and documented the stories of elderly Zuni speakers while undertaking a translation of the Bible into the Zuni language during the 1960s and 1970s. Sound recordings (1964-1967) include narratives told by Zuni storytellers Longkeena Nash and Tom Ideque and others; recordings of children reading high school reports in English; and Curtis Cook reciting the gospel acccording to St. Mark, and other recordings. Photographs (1964-1972) include pictures of some of the Zuni speakers and storytellers who aided Cook in learning the Zuni language; landscapes at and near Zuni; adobe brick making and daily occupations at Zuni; photographs documenting the Zuni entry of dancers and musicians at the Gallup Intertribal Ceremonial in 1965; Zuni children; Zuni artwork, including jewelry and pottery. Manuscripts include Zuni stories and translation exercises in Zuni, and some interlineal translations in English of Zuni recordings from the Doris Duke collection. Cook submitted notes describing his photographs and his work at Zuni in 2004. On February 14, 2005, Curtis Cook met with staff of the American Folklife Center to discuss this collection and his work in Zuni. An audio recording of this meeting is included in the collection.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Cook, Curtis D.
Organizations
American Folklife Center.
Subjects
Songs, Zuni.; Storytelling--New Mexico--Zuni.; Tales--New Mexico--Zuni.; Zuni Indians--Folklore.; Zuni Indians--Missions.; Zuni Indians--New Mexico--Zuni--Photographs.; Zuni Indians--New Mexico--Zuni--Social life and customs.; Zuni language--Glossaries, vocabularies, etc.; Zuni language--Orthography and spelling.; Zuni language--Study and teaching.; Zuni literature--New Mexico--Zuni.
Places
Black Rock (N.M.)--Social life and customs.; Zuni (N.M.)--Social life and customs.
Titles
Bible. Mark. Zuni
Form/Genre
Field recordings.; Folk tales.; Personal narratives.; Photographs.
Arrangement
The manuscript material is the first series in this collection, in Boxes 1-3 (Folders 1-53). For the most part, the manuscripts are arranged chronologically by date of creation.
The second series contains the sound recordings, SR01-SR06. The original reel-to-reel tape boxes were retained to preserve the notes on the box labels and are stored in Box 4.
The final series consists of the graphic images. Slides 1-196 and photographs ph1-ph20 are arranged in numerical order according to the sequential numbers assigned by the donor, Curtis Cook, and are stored in Box 5 of the collection. Captions and notes for the images, as assigned by Curtis Cook, are also stored in Box 5.
Acquisition
Curtis D. Cook; 2004.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Access to recordings may be restricted. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Biographical Notes
In 1964, Curtis Cook worked with the Zuni Pueblo as a member of Wycliffe Bible Translators, an international organization that translates the Bible into local languages. Cook was given the Zuni name, "Chummali," or locust, because he actively conversed with everyone in the village. A year after he arrived, the written alphabet for the Zuni language was developed and a few small pamphlets and literacy manuals were published to assist the Zuni in creating a written record in their own language.
Scope and Content
Collection of field recordings, photographs, and notes by linguist Curtis Cook, who learned the Zuni language and documented the stories of elderly Zuni speakers while undertaking a translation of the Bible into the Zuni language during the 1960s and 1970s. Sound recordings (1964-1967) include narratives told by Zuni storytellers Longkeena Nash and Tom Ideque and others; recordings of children reading high school reports in English; and Curtis Cook reciting the gospel acccording to St. Mark, and other recordings. Photographs (1964-1972) include pictures of some of the Zuni speakers and storytellers who aided Cook in learning the Zuni language; landscapes at and near Zuni; adobe brick making and daily occupations at Zuni; photographs documenting the Zuni entry of dancers and musicians at the Gallup Intertribal Ceremonial in 1965; Zuni children; Zuni artwork, including jewelry and pottery. Manuscripts include Zuni stories and translation exercises in Zuni, and some interlineal translations in English of Zuni recordings from the Doris Duke collection. Cook submitted notes describing his photographs and his work at Zuni in 2004. On February 14, 2005, Curtis Cook met with staff of the American Folklife Center to discuss this collection and his work in Zuni, an audio recording of this meeting is included in the collection.
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  Administrative, Correspondence, Index, Field Notes, and Articles
  - Finding Aid (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Notes Clarifying Orthographic Representation and Interpretation, February 1965., 6 pages. (Box-folder 1/2)
    A summary of the linguistic committee consultation written by Curtis Cook.
  - A Proposed Zuni Orthography, September 1965., 5 pages. (Box-folder 1/3)
    Explanation of reasons for orthographic choices listing phonetic sounds of the Zuni alphabet. Submitted by Curtis Cook to the Summer Institue of Linguistics for review.
  - The Zuni Lanuguage: A Phonemic Statement, September 4, 1965., 75 pages. (Box-folder 1/4)
    Technical paper describing the sound and syllable system of the Zuni language. Prerequisite to the development of practical orthography. Submitted by Curtis Cook for approval by the Summer Institute of Linguistics.
  - Inventory of Zuni Sounds and Practical Orthographic Representations, 1965-1966, 6 pages. (Box-folder 1/5)
    Submitted by Curtis Cook and approved in September 1966 at Branch Conference.
  - Letter of Acceptance from Dr. Irvine Davis. Linguistic consultant for the Summer Institute of Linguistics, September 13, 1965., 2 pages. (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Zuni Language Features, 1970, 7 pages. (Box-folder 1/7)
    Zuni onomatopoeia and Zuni pronouns and verb classes prepared by Curtis Cook for use in Zuni language classes.
  - God An Bena:We K'okshi. Mark Ts'ina:Washkowa. (Gospel of Mark), Circa 1970., 339 pages. (Box-folder 1/8 - 12)
    First Draft of the Gospel of Mark in Zuni. Handwritten in phonetic transcription with partial interlinear English translation and with edits.
  - God An Bena:We K'okshi. Mark Ts'ina:washkowa, 1970, 110 pages. (Box-folder 1/13)
    The Gospel of Mark translated by Mr. And Mrs. Curtis Cook with Rex Chimoni, Lorenzo Chavez, Floyd Owaleon, and Johnny Cheama. Published by Wycliffe Bible Translators, Inc., Eastlake, Colorado.
  - Suski, 1971, 83 pages. (Box-folder 1/14)
    Coyote Stories in Zuni and in English as told by Lorenzo Chavez. Transcribed and translated by Curtis Cook. Published by the Summer Institute of Linguistics, Zuni, New Mexico.
  - Coyote and Crow. Coyote and Locust, Circa 1971., 6 pages. (Box-folder 1/15)
    A free translation by Curtis Cook of two of the three Zuni folk tales in Suski.
  - Ho'n A:Wan Delapna:We. (Our Stories), 1972, 42 pages. (Box-folder 1/16)
    Collection of self-authored stories by Zuni students in grades 5-8 at the Zuni Christian Reformed Mission School. Published by Gallup-Mckinley County Schools, Gallup, New Mexico.
  - Zuni Literacy Teacher's Guide, November 1972., 57 pages. (Box-folder 1/17)
    A set of literacy lesson plans illustrating Zuni alphabet, word-building charts, and reading drills by Curtis Cook. Published by Gallup-Mckinley County Schools Follow Through, Gallup, New Mexico.
  - A Glossary of Common Zuni Terms, 1973, 14 pages. (Box-folder 1/18)
    English to Zuni translation of common vocabulary words edited by Wilfred Eriacho. Published by The Pueblo of Zuni, Zuni, New Mexico.
  - Kya:k Hołi. (Long Ago), 1974, 24 pages. (Box-folder 1/19)
    Zuni transcription of three old stories by Lokina and Diwla. Transcribed by Wilfred Eriacho. Edited by Wilfred Eriacho and Curtis Cook. Published by The Pueblo of Zuni, Zuni, New Mexico.
  - Zuni Tribal Oath of Office, Circa 1975., 9 pages. (Box-folder 1/20)
    Handwritten notes and typed oath in Zuni translated into Zuni by Curtis Cook.
  - A:shiwi A:wan An'ułłanakya Haydoshnan:we, Circa 1975., 66 pages. (Box-folder 1/21)
    (Zuni Tribal Constitution Articles I, II, and III.) English and Zuni versions of the Zuni tribal consitution.
  - Nucleus and Margin of Zuni Clause Types, May 15, 1975., 37 pages. (Box-folder 2/22)
    A booklet containing this technical article by Curtis Cook published in Linguistics by Mouton and Co., The Hague, The Netherlands.
  - Ulohnan ibałdok'yan ihap, kop leyadinna? (When the world is about to end, what will happen?), 1976, 18 pages. (Box-folder 2/23)
    A booklet translated by Curtis Cook relating to events surrounding a recent earthquake to the book of Matthew, Chapter 24. Published by Wycliffe Bible Translators, Inc. Eastlake, Colorado.
  - Acts. Kwa'hol God an Duda'tsi:kwe Lewunapkowa. (What God's disciples did), 1978, 209 pages. (Box-folder 2/24)
    A translation of the Book of Acts by Curtis Cook with Rex Chimoni, Lorenzo Chavez. Published by The World Home Bible League, South Holland, Illinois, and The Canadian Home Bible League, Weston, Ontario.
  - Gospel of John in Zuni. [1 of 6], September 7, 1978., 150 pages. (Box-folder 2/25 - 30)
    Handwritten first draft of the Gospel of John in the Zuni language by Curtis Cook. Notebook 1 contains Chapters 1:1-4:36 (first draft).
  - Gospel of John in Zuni. [2 of 6], September 7, 1978., 130 pages. (Box-folder 2/26)
    Handwritten first draft of the Gospel of John in the Zuni language by Curtis Cook. Notebook 2 contains Chapters 1:1-5:20 (second draft).
  - Gospel of John in Zuni. [3 of 6], September 7, 1978., 130 pages. (Box-folder 2/27)
    Handwritten first draft of the Gospel of John in the Zuni language by Curtis Cook. Notebook 3 contains Chapters 5:20-8:48.
  - Gospel of John in Zuni. [4 of 6], September 7, 1978., 70 pages. (Box-folder 2/28)
    Handwritten first draft of the Gospel of John in the Zuni language by Curtis Cook. Notebook 4 contains Chapters 8:49-11:21.
  - Gospel of John in Zuni. [5 of 6], September 7, 1978., 130 pages. (Box-folder 2/29)
    Handwritten first draft of the Gospel of John in the Zuni language by Curtis Cook. Notebook 5 contains Chapters 11:22-16:11.
  - Gospel of John in Zuni. [6 of 6], September 7, 1978., 144 pages. (Box-folder 2/30)
    Handwritten first draft of the Gospel of John in the Zuni language by Curtis Cook. Notebook 6 contains Chapters 16:12-21:25.
  - Gospel of John in Zuni, Chapters 1-6, September 1978., 31 pages. (Box-folder 3/31)
    Second draft of the Gospel of John in the Zuni language by Curtis Cook with interlinear English translation.
  - The Zuni Language, September 1979., 19 pages. (Box-folder 3/32)
    A paper prepared by Curtis Cook for inclusion in a series of presentations by Dr. Robert Rebert of the University of New Mexico.
  - Back Translation (Zuni to English) of the final draft of the Gospel of John, Chapters 1-4, August 4, 1985., 81 pages. (Box-folder 3/33)
    Handwritten back translation of the final draft of the Gospel of John translated by Curtis Cook. The back translation illustrates Zuni patterns of expression and translation alternatives.
  - Gospel of John. Final, undated., 192 pages. (Box-folder 3/34)
    Typed final draft of the Gospel of John translated by Curtis Cook.
  - Historical Narrative. Horse Racing. Kanteena #7, undated., 11 pages. (Box-folder 3/35)
    Handwritten transcription in Zuni with interlinear English translation. Kanteena #7 refers to the name of the narrator on the corresponding reel number of the recording in the Doris Duke Collection.
  - Chummali dap Ommali. Tape #13B Awelagte, undated., 10 pages. (Box-folder 3/36)
    Handwritten transcription in Zuni. Tape #13B Awelagte refers to the name of the narrator on the corresponding reel number of the recording in the Doris Duke Collection.
  - Syntax, undated., 4 pages. (Box-folder 3/37)
    Handwritten classroom exercise in Zuni with English translations.
  - Three Fragments of Zuni Translations, undated., 5 pages. (Box-folder 3/38)
    Handwritten translations in Zuni and English.
  - Sonda:lu:kwe dap Suski, undated., 2 pages. (Box-folder 3/39)
    Typed transliteration in Zuni of Zuni narrative.
  - Aktsek Ts'an dap K'yana Łana, undated., 2 pages. (Box-folder 3/40)
  - Suski dap Donashi. Coyote and Badger, undated., 28 pages. (Box-folder 3/41)
    Typed Zuni narrative in Zuni and English.
  - Suski dap K'walashi. Coyote and Crow, undated., 10 pages. (Box-folder 3/42)
  - Mu:kwi, undated., 9 pages. (Box-folder 3/43)
    Handwritten Zuni narrative in Zuni.
  - For Newsletter, undated., 1 page. (Box-folder 3/44)
    Handwritten draft of an open letter written by Curtis Cook about his project to translate Bible into Zuni using a "new way to write."
  - My days with Buffalo Bill. Tom Ideque, undated., 11 pages. (Box-folder 3/45)
    Handwritten of transcription of Zuni narrative in Zuni with interlinear English translation. Narrated by Tom Ideque. Corresponds to sound recording SR02.
  - Aktsek'i Okna'kowa. Parable of the Lost Son. Rex Chimoni, undated., 11 pages. (Box-folder 3/46)
    Handwritten and typed versions of biblical parable from Luke 15:11-24 in Zuni and English. Translated by Rex Chimoni.
  - Doye:nona dap Do:sho:we. The Sower and the Seeds, April 12, 1966., 6 pages. (Box-folder 3/47)
    Correspondence regarding translation of biblical parable from Mark 4. Typed free translation in English. Typed practical orthography in Zuni with handwritten interlinear translations in English and a phonetic transcription in Zuni.
  - What Happened at Halona:kwi, undated., 32 pages. (Box-folder 3/48)
    Two typed transcriptions of a Zuni narrative in Zuni with interlinear translations in English.
  - Chummali dap Suski. Locust and Coyote, undated., 32 pages. (Box-folder 3/49)
    Handwritten and typed versions of a Zuni narrative in Zuni and English. Notation of a Zuni Folk Song, "Chummali, Chummali, Sho koya."
  - Naming of Halona, undated., 59 pages. (Box-folder 3/50)
    Handwritten transcriptions of a Zuni narrative in Zuni with interlinear translations in English by Floyd Owaleon.
  - O:yih Tsawak'i. Deer Woman Raises Son of Sun, May 1961., 121 pages. (Box-folder 3/51)
    Futurist Interpretation of Revelation. Handwritten transcriptions of a Zuni narrative in Zuni with interlinear translations in English by Pauline Cook.
  - Formulary for Profession of Faith/Baptism by Rex Natewa, undated., 3 pages. (Box-folder 3/52)
    Handwritten in Zuni.
  - Becker, Ross. Written Zuni Language is Pueblo's New Goal. Gallup Independent, February 14, 1976., 2 pages. (Box-folder 3/53)
    Original clipping and preservation copy of an article about the Zuni Language Development Program and the role of Curtis Cook in the program.
  - Wood, April. Translator returns to Zuni Pueblo. The Independent, July 20, 1985., 2 pages. (Box-folder 3/54)
    Original clipping and preservation copy of an article about Curtis Cook and his work to develop a written alphabet for the Zuni language.
- Series II: Sound Recordings
  - Chimoni Conversa. Spoken by Zuni storyteller Ideque, undated., sound tape reel, analog; 7 in.; 1800 ft.; AFC 2004/010: SR01
  - "My Days w/ Buffalo Bill ‐ Tom I." / "Zuni Slide Program (Feb. ‘67)", 1967-02, sound tape reel, analog; 7 in.; 1200 ft.; AFC 2004/010: SR02
  - "Casset Tapes" (sic), undated., sound tape reel, analog; 7 in.; 1200 ft.; AFC 2004/010: SR03
  - "Deer Woman Raises Son of Sun. Naming of Halona." Spoken by Zuni Storyteller Longkeena Nash. [Tape 1 of 2], undated., sound tape reel, analog; 7 in.; 1200 ft.; AFC 2004/010: SR04
  - "Deer Woman Raises Son of Sun. Naming of Halona." Spoken by Zuni Storyteller Longkeena Nash. [Tape 2 of 2], undated., sound tape reel, analog; 7 in.; 1200 ft.; AFC 2004/010: SR05
  - Curtis Cook discussing his work with the Zuni Pueblo and the collection material, 2005-02-14, audiocassette; 90-minute; AFC 2004/010: SR06
    Curtis Cook meeting with American Folklife Staff. February 14, 2005. Sound recording of collection donor, Curtis Cook, discussing his work with the Zuni Pueblo and the collection material. American Folklife Center Conference Room.
  - Original reel-to-reel tape boxes, 5 empty boxes (Box 4)
    The original reel-to-reel tape boxes were retained to preserve the notes on the box labels.
- Series III: Photographs
  Image descriptions provided by Curtis Cook.
  - The first old man I met at Zuni (name unknown), September, 1963, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 1 (Box 5)
    This was on my first visit to Zuni on the way back from my last year of training in linguistics at the University of Oklahoma. Upon arriving at Zuni, I began to walk around the village, and came across this old man. The old man's daughter stepped out of her house when I stopped to visit with him. She spoke English, so I asked her how to tell the old man "Hello." Then I asked her to ask him to let me take his picture. He consented, so I took the picture, then asked his daughter how to say "thank you" in Zuni. I took the picture, and said, "Elahkwa." I was speaking Zuni.
  - Rex Natewa, my first language helper, 1965, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 2 (Box 5)
    He was the native pastor of the Christian Reformed Mission at Zuni.
  - Rex Natewa, my first language helper, 1965, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 3 (Box 5)
    Rex was a literalist, when it came to teaching me to speak Zuni. I asked him how I would tell someone, "I'm glad (that) you came," after they had visited me. His response in Zuni was two separate declarative statements: "I'm glad" and "You came". Neither statement had anything to do with the other. Rex passed away in 1965. I was at his bedside, when he died.
  - Longkeena Nash, the storyteller, 1967, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 4 (Box 5)
    Photo taken in front of my home at Zuni in 1967.
  - Longkeena Nash, the storyteller, 1965-1977, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 5 (Box 5)
    Longkeena would sometimes stop by after going to the trading post.
  - Longkeena, 1965-1977, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 6 (Box 5)
    Almost all of my early language learning was in visits such as this with old men. Consequently, I learned an older dialect of Zuni; so much so that a high schooler in the literacy class I taught in summer school commented: "Cook, he talks like an old man."
  - Na:dusa (Lorenzo Chavez), my primary language helper, 1965-1973, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 7 (Box 5)
  - Na:dusa (Lorenzo Chavez), 1965-1977, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 8 (Box 5)
    Lorenzo was believed to be in his late 90's when I first met him.
  - Na:dusa (Lorenzo Chavez), 1965-1977, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 9 (Box 5)
    My times with Lorenzo, were among the richest and most memorable of my entire fifteen years at Zuni.
  - Old man Lashhina Hu'tsi, Owaleon Nash, 1965-1977, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 10 (Box 5)
    Old man Lashhina Hu'tsi, Owaleon Nash, believed to have been over 100 years old in this picture.
  - Old man Lashhina Hu'tsi, Owaleon Nash, 1965-1977, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 11 (Box 5)
    In a session with Owaleon Nash, I was trying to find an equivalent term for the Biblical concept of "repentance." I told him in Zuni that "repentance" was what you do when you are walking one direction on your road of life (an appropriate metaphor in Zuni for one's personal conduct), and you decide that you're not walking the right way; so you "change your road" (i.e., "you change your behavior"). After giving the idea some thought, he said "How can I change my road? I'm a Zuni."
  - At work once again with Lorenzo Chavez, 1965-1977, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 12 (Box 5)
  - Lorenzo and I spent many hours at his small house at Ojo Caliente, a farming village 13 miles west of Zuni village, 1965-1973, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 13 (Box 5)
  - Lorenzo Chavez, 1965-1977, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 14 (Box 5)
    Lorenzo was always sharp, and had an exceptional memory. His input into the translation work was extremely reliable, and he was so highly respected among the people that it was very much to my advantage to have used him as my primary language helper.
  - For several years, when we lived in a small house behind the Vanderwagen Trading Post, I did my work in a small camping trailer next to the house, 1965-1977, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 15 (Box 5)
  - In my new study at Blackrock, 5 miles east of Zuni village, where we lived from 1972 to 1977, 1972-1973, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 16 (Box 5)
  - In my study, 1972-1973, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 17 (Box 5)
    In my study, I maintained a very rigorous schedule, working 9-10 hours a day, doing something in which I took great delight; but I also sought to balance desk work with visiting in the village, affording me opportunities to hear and to speak the language in different contexts.
  - At my desk, 1965-1973, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 18 (Box 5)
    At my desk – using several commentaries, and English translations of the Bible, as well as the original Greek text, I prepared the first draft to be checked for accuracy with a Zuni speaker later.
  - At my desk, 1965-1973, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 19 (Box 5)
    At my desk – the translation was checked periodically by an experienced translation consultant from the Summer Institute of Linguistics. The checking sessions were conducted with a native speaker present, and the consultants concluded that the Zuni translation was of highest quality, in terms of both its faithfulness to the original text and accuracy, communicating the right concepts to native speakers.
  - Peter Neha, 1965-1977, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 20 (Box 5)
    I spent a only a short time in my translation work with Peter Neha, father of fourteen children. He was kept busy with his livelihood: making adobe bricks (see slides 141-149). (NOTE) Unfortunately, I do not have photographs of several others who helped me with the translation from time to time. Among them, Rex Chimoni, who was native pastor at the Christian Reformed Mission after the passing of Rex Natewa. Mr. Chimoni became a very good friend, and was an excellent language helper. Other helpers were: Arthur and Floyd Owaleon, and Lincoln Harker, Spencer Nashboo, and John Cheama.
  - Zuni welcoming sign at the northern reservation boundary, 1963-1978, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 21 (Box 5)
  - Zuni mesas in the distance, 1963-1972, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 22 (Box 5)
  - Mesas to the south of the sacred mountain, Dowa Yalanne ("corn mountain"), 1963-1976, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 23 (Box 5)
  - Aerial view of Zuni village, 1963-1978, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 24 (Box 5)
  - Zuni village at sunset (from the south side of the Zuni river), 1963-1970, 35 mm color slide; AFC 2004/010: 25 (Box 5)